Finding aid to the Valerie Harms papers SSC.MS.00288
Sophia Smith Collection
Valerie Harms papers
1940-2014
Sophia Smith Collection
Harms, Valerie
SSC.MS.00288
16 boxes (16.25 linear feet)
Publisher, Magic Circle Press; Editor; Consultant; Instructor; Therapist. The Papers include personal and professional correspondence; articles; proposals; unpublished manuscripts, notes, and research files for Harms' writings, including Voices From Within: Women Prisoner's Poetry, and her unpublished novels; copies of her books; Magic Circle Press material; conference and workshop material on the "Intensive Journal method"; and audio tapes from "Celebration with Nin" and the "Myth I" and II conferences.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections. This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by Valerie Harms in 1995-2015. Accession numbers: 95S-44, 10S-12, 10S-38, 13S-29, 15S-20.
Biographical / Historical
Valerie Harms (1940-) was born in Chicago, later moved to Texas as a teen. She earned A.B. from Smith College in English in 1962; married Laurence F. Sheehan (divorced 1981), and had 2 children. In 1955 she started one of the first Elvis Presley fan clubs in west Texas. She lived in France for 3 years; co-founded a Montessori School in Connecticut. Her 1st book, Unmasking: Ten Women in Metamorphosis (1973) grew out of involvement with group of feminists in the arts. Later she co-founded Magic Circle Press, a publication company for books by women. She also edited the journal Celebration in 1973 with Anais Nin, her friend and mentor. Harms has studied and practiced Depth Psychology, Jungian analysis and Intensive Journal Method since the 1970s. Other books she's written include Stars in my Sky: Nin/ Montessori/ Skloff (1976); a biography of Elvis Presley (1977); and Inner Lover: Using Passion as a Way to Self-Empowerment (1992). Recently she's been involved in environmental science, editing the journal of the National Audobon Society, (1987- ). She also wrote the National Audobon Society Almanac of the Environment/Ecology of Everyday Life (1994). Harms organized first Women Writers Conference. She consults, gives workshops and private counseling since 1980.
Other Finding Aids
This online finding aid currently provides detailed description of only the most recent additions to this collection. Additional materials are described in unpublished lists that can be sent to you upon request by contacting specialcollections@smith.edu
Scope and Contents
The Valerie Harms Papers include personal and professional correspondence; articles; proposals; unpublished manuscripts, notes, and research files for writings, including Voices From Within: Women Prisoner's Poetry, as well as unpublished novels; copies of her books; Magic Circle Press material; conference and workshop material on the "Intensive Journal method"; and audio tapes from "Celebration with Nin" and the "Myth I" and II conferences.
Diaries--authorship; Creative writing--Study and teaching; Group relations training-United States--History--Sources; Publishers and publishing--United States--History--Sources; Small presses--United States; Women--Psychology; Women publishers--United States--Biography--Sources; Feminists--United States--Biography--Sources; Authors, American--20th century--Biography--Sources; Environmental protection--United States-History--20th century--Sources; Feminism and art--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Feminism--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Women authors, American--20th century--Biography--Sources; correspondence; Writings; Audiotapes; Negatives; Contact sheets; photographs; Ephemera; Books; Harms, Valerie; Magic Circle Press--History--Sources; Smith College--Students--History--Sources; Steloff, Frances, 1887-; Montessori, Maria, 1870-1952; Nin, Anais, 1903-1977; Presley, Elvis, 1935-1977; Progoff, Ira; Harms, Valerie
- Valerie Harms correspondence, writings and related materials, 1985-2009; 2010-S-0038; Harms, Valerie; 0.75 linear feet (2 boxes)
  Harms, Valerie
  - Published books and articles, typescripts, materials related to publishing and correspondence, 1985-2009; 2010-S-0038 (Box 1)
- Magic Circle Press materials, 1976-1990; 2010-S-0012; 0.75 linear feet (2 boxes)
  - Correspondence, contracts, typescripts, notes, photographs and miscellaneous materials related to Magic Circle Press, 1976-1999; 2010-S-0012 (Box 1)
  - Anais Nin "Waste of Timelessness and Other Early Stories" typescript, photographs and notes, 1970-1979; 2010-S-0012 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous memorabelia, undated; 2010-S-0012 (Box 2)
- Valerie Harms personal correspondence, photographs and published works by Harms and others, 1959-2013; 2013-S-0029; Harms, Valerie; 1 linear feet (1 box)
  - Correspondence related to "Tryin' to Get Back to You" and original inscribed photographs of Elvis Presley, 1986-2000; 1999-2000; 2013-S-0029 (Box 1)
  - "Elizabeth's Memorial", 2003; 2013-S-0029 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Elizabeth Hatcher, 1982-1985; 2013-S-0029 (Box 1)
  - Photograph albulms, undated; 2013-S-0029 (Box 1)
  - Calendars, 1959-1961; 2013-S-0029 (Box 1)
  - "Juggling, 1962-1987," Smith College Reunion, undated; 2013-S-0029 (Box 1)
  - Smith friends' wedding invitations, announcements and correspondence including note from Eudora Welty, 1961-1969; 2013-S-0029 (Box 1)
  - Biographical aterials, 2013; undated; 2013-S-0029 (Box 1)
  - Six books by Harms, 1973-2005; 2013-S-0029 (Box 1)
    General
    Almanac of the Environemnt: The Ecology of Everyday Life (1994) Dreaming of Abimals: Dialogue Between Self and World (2005) The Inner Lover: Using Passion as a Way to Self-Empowerment (1992, 1999) Maria Montessouri, Anais Nin, Frances Steloff: Stars in My Sky (1976) Tryin' to Get to You: The Story of Elvis OPresleyt (1979, 2000) Unmasking: Ten Women in Metamorphosis (1973)
  - Books "Gatherings from a Dancer's Journal" by Carolyn Bildbach and "Waste of Timelesssness and Other Early Stories" by Anais Nin, 1992; 1977; 2013-S-0029 (Box 1)
- Valerie Harms published books and article and family photographs, 1940-2014; 2015-S-0020; 0.5 linear feet (1 box)
  - Published books and articles, 1989-2013; 2015-S-0020 (Box 1)
  - Articles by and about Jan Beyea, 1990-1991; 2015-S-0020 (Box 1)
  - Distinctly Montana summer and fall issues, Valerie Harms, editor, 2014; 2015-S-0020 (Box 1)
  - Family photographs, 1940-2014; 2015-S-0020 (Box 1)